Guide to the Dannreuther Family Papers, 1836-1988 (bulk 1875-1925)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Dannreuther Family Papers
1836-1988
1875-1925
Dannreuther Family
6.75 cubic feet (16 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, date books, sheet music, programs, clippings and scrapbooks relating to the Dannreuther Family, especially the musical careers of Gustav and Nellie Dannreuther.
Biographical Note
Gustav Dannreuther (21 July 1853 - 19 Dec 1923) was a violinist, instructor and founding member of the Dannreuther String Quartet. He was the son of Abraham Dannreuther and Sophie Fischbacker. His brother was the pianist Edward Dannreuther.
Ellen "Nellie" Morton Taylor Dannreuther (25 May 1858 - 3 July 1942), Gustav's wife, was also a noted musician. She was a pianist who performed on her own as well as with her husband. She was also an instructor, teaching privately and also for a period at Wells College. She was the daughter of Martin Taylor and Martha Gooding. Gustav and Nellie married 12 July 1882 and had three children: Walter Taylor Dannreuther, Martin Taylor Dannreuther, and Gustav Dannreuther, Jr.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, date books, sheet music, programs, clippings and scrapbooks relating to the Dannreuther Family, especially the musical careers of Gustav and Nellie Dannreuther. Of particular note are the letters from Nellie Dannreuther to her parents while she was studying in Leipzig from 1875-1876. Related letters can be found in the correspondence of Nellie Morton, Nellie Dannreuther's aunt who served as chaperone for her and two other Buffalo girls during the trip.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The chamber music belonging to the Dannreuther String Quartet was given to Vassar College by Gustav Dannreuther in 1919-1920. Much of the practical performing material was absorbed into Vassar's George Sherman Dickinson Music Library collection.
Subject Headings
Names:
Dannreuther, Gustav; Dannreuther, Ellen
Organizations:
Dannreuther String Quartet
Subjects:
Musicians--Correspondence; Music--Instruction and study--Germany; Music--Germany--Leipzig--19th century
Places:
Leipzig (Germany)--Description and travel
Document Types:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Photographs; Printed ephemera; Scrapbooks
VCL Categories:
Family; Music; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, August 2009. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, October 2025.
Acquisition Information
15 Dannreuther scrapbooks were transferred from the Vassar College Music Library in 2009. They were loaned to that library by Nellie Dannreuther, presumably after Gustav died in 1923. The rest of the collection was given by Susan Dannreuther, July 2009.
Series List
- Series I. Gustav Dannreuther's Diaries and Date Books, 1871-1922; (Boxes 5-10)
  The dates and the contents of the date books in this series overlap. One set is mostly personal while the other two are primarily professional.
- Series II. Correspondence, 1858-1988; (Box 11)
  Correspondence of significance in this series includes Nellie Dannreuther's letters home while she was studying in Leipzig, Gustav Dannreuther's letters to Nellie while he was away from home, and letters from "Auntie" Dickson, the Dannreuther's nanny, to Nellie as well as the children. Other correspondents include Nellie's aunt, Nellie Morton, and her granddaughter (Alice and Martin Taylor Dannnreuther's daughter) Susan Dannreuther.
- Series III. Scrapbooks and Clippings, circa 1865-1963; (Boxes 11-15)
  Several volumes as well as loose material, most documenting the musical careers of Nellie and Gustav Dannreuther.
- Series IV. Ephemera, 1878-1940; (Boxes 9-11)
  Programs from musical performances as well as other miscellany.
- Series V. Photographs, circa 1910-1940; (Boxes 2-4, 10, 16)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous, 1884-1918; (Boxes 1, 10-12, 16)
Container List
- Series I. Gustav Dannreuther's Diaries and Date Books
  - Diaries, 1905-1914; (8 volumes and 2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Diaries, 1915-1922; (8 volumes) (Box 6)
  - Date books, 1901-1914; (5 folders of loose sheets) (Box 7)
  - Date books, 1877-1901; (15 volumes) (Box 8)
  - Date books, 1902-1912; (11 volumes) (Box 9)
  - Notebook, circa 1871-1872; (1 volume with enclosures) (Box 8)
  - Notebook, circa 1901; (1 volume) (Box 10)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Dannreuther, Alice Evans to Mr. and Mrs. H.C. Evans, 1918-1921 (Folder 11.1)
  - Dannreuther, Gustav to Nellie Dannreuther, 1881, 1889 (Folder 11.2)
  - Dannreuther, Gustav to Nellie Dannreuther, 1909-1910 (Folder 11.3)
  - Dannreuther, Gustav to Nellie Dannreuther, 1920 (Folder 11.4)
  - Dannreuther, Gustav to miscellaneous, 1889, 1904, 1920, 1923 (Folder 11.5)
  - Dannreuther, Gustav, Jr. to Gustav Dannreuther, 1920 (Folder 11.6)
  - Dannreuther, Martin Taylor to Nellie and Gustav Dannreuther, 1899-1904 (Folder 11.7)
  - Dannreuther, Martin Taylor to Nellie and Gustav Dannreuther, 1912-1923 (Folder 11.8)
  - Dannreuther, Martin Taylor to Susan Dannreuther, 1926-1933, undated (Folder 11.9)
  - Dannreuther, Martin Taylor to Mr. and Mrs. H.C. Evans, 1916-1929 (Folder 11.10)
  - Dannreuther, Martin Taylor to and from miscellaneous, 1904-1965 (Folder 11.11)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1870-1875 (Folder 11.12)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1876 Jan - Feb (Folder 11.13)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1876 Mar - May (Folder 11.14)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1876 June - Aug (Folder 11.15)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1878-1890 (Folder 11.16)
  - Dannreuther, Nellie to miscellaneous, 1874-1875, undated (Folder 11.17)
  - Dannreuther, Susan to Taylor and Alice Dannreuther, 1927-1966, undated (Folder 11.18)
  - Dannreuther, Susan to and from miscellaneous, 1966-1988 (Folder 11.19)
  - Dickson, "Auntie" to Nellie Dannreuther, 1888, 1890 1892 (Folder 11.20)
  - Dickson, "Auntie" to Nellie Dannreuther, 1893-1894 (Folder 11.21)
  - Dickson, "Auntie" to Walter and Taylor Dannreuther, 1893-1906 (Folder 11.22)
  - Morton, Ellen "Nellie" to Nellie Dannreuther, 1882, undated (Folder 11.23)
  - Morton, Ellen "Nellie" to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1864-1866 (Folder 11.24)
  - Morton, Ellen "Nellie" to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1867-1874 (Folder 11.25)
  - Morton, Ellen "Nellie" to Martha and Martin Taylor, 1875-1880, undated (Folder 11.26)
  - Morton, Ellen "Nellie" to miscellaneous, circa 1875-1876 (Folder 11.27)
  - Taylor, Martin to his family, 1858-1859, 1875-1880 (Folder 11.28)
  - Miscellaneous to Alice Dannreuther, 1950-1962, undated (Folder 11.29)
  - Miscellaneous to Gustav Dannreuther, 1876-1922 (Folder 11.30)
  - Miscellaneous to Nellie Dannreuther, 1873-1896, 1907, undated (Folder 11.31)
  - Miscellaneous Dannreuther Family concerning Gustav's death, 1923 (Folder 11.32)
  - Miscellaneous Evans/Dannreuther Family, 1916-1949 (Folder 11.33)
  - Miscellaneous Taylor Family, 1836-1891 (Folder 11.34)
  - Miscellaneous, 1914-1945, undated (Folder 11.35)
- Series III. Scrapbooks and Clippings
  - Scrapbook of Gustav and Nellie Dannreuther family material, 1882-1963; (includes list) (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook ofBerkshire Gleanerclippings as well as earlier family-related clippings and ephemera, 1881-1910 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings and ephemera related to the Dannreuther's musical careers, including the Dannreuther Quartet and the Beethoven String Quartet, ca 1865 - 1922; (15 volumes) (Boxes 13-15)
  - Scrapbook of Chamber Music Club material, 1889-1900 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook of Yale University Chamber Music concerts, 1888-1896 (Box 12)
  - Loose scrapbook of material about Edward Dannreuther and other composers, undated (Box 12)
  - Loose clippings regarding the Dannreuther Quartet — research photocopies, undated (Folder 11.36)
  - Loose clippings regarding the Dannreuther Quartet — originals, undated (Folder 11.37)
- Series IV. Ephemera
  - Programs, 1878-1912, 1940 (Folder 11.38)
  - Programs — laminated, 1908, 1923, undated (Folder 11.39)
  - Programs — oversized, undated (Box 10)
  - Gustav Dannreuther's calling cards, undated; (3 cards in a leather sleeve) (Box 9)
  - Booklets, etc., undated (Folder 11.40)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 11.41)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Gustav Dannreuther, undated (Boxes 3-4)
  - Gustav Dannreuther, undated (Boxe 16)
  - Nellie Taylor Dannreuther, undated (Boxes 3-4)
  - Dannreuther Children, undated (Boxes 3-4)
  - Other Family and Friends, undated (Boxes 3-4)
  - Musicians (including Dannreuther String Quartet), undated (Boxes 3-4)
  - Dannreuther String Quartet, undated (Boxes 10, 16)
  - Miscellaneous negatives, circa 1910-1940 (Box 2)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous
  - Family and genealogical material, undated (Folders 11.42-11.44)
  - Nellie and Gustav Dannreuther, undated (Folder 11.45)
  - Nellie and Gustav Dannreuther — Finances, undated (Folder 11.46)
  - Gustav Dannreuther — Publishing contract for his violin studies book, 1892 (Box 10)
  - Gustav Dannreuther — Bound, annotated sheet music, undated; (2 volumes) (Box 12)
  - Gustav Dannreuther — Address book, undated (Box 12)
  - Martin Taylor Dannreuther — Death, undated (Folder 11.47)
  - Martin Taylor Dannreuther — Business records, undated (Folders 11.48 - 11.49)
  - Edward Dannreuther, undated (Folder 11.50)
  - Dannreuther Quintet — Finances, undated (Folder 11.51)
  - Dannreuther Quartet — Account book for "Orchestra Engagements,", 1901-1910 (Box 12)
  - Dannreuther piano sale, undated (Folder 11.52)
  - William C. Cornwell's Book of the Programmes of the Buffalo Philharmonic Society, 1884-1885; (2 copies) (Box 10)
  - Musical Mutual Protective Union directories, 1891-1918; (23 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Philharmonic Society of New York, 1890-1906; (1 folder) (Box 10)
  - Painting of Walter Dannreuther's home in Lee, MA, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous musical manuscripts, undated (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 11.53)